[Music]
So welcome to
Lamrim and L means steps on the
path and this is for
me and I'm having lunch.
I don't have a butt, I
have a... I had lunch with my
mother-in-law.
She
died, and she
had a friend who later kicked herself out,
which you should do with friends. And
we had lunch
and asked what is the greatest, the best
book in the whole world. And
I love books, so it was a very
difficult question for me to choose, but
I think that what
we are studying here is the greatest
book on this planet in this
universe. And my teacher taught it to me
three times. It took 30 years,
and each time he finished, he started again.
And he taught it in two
different
places, once in Washington
and one place in Ork. He
's a
driver, so I was able to
attend both. So I
attended both classes for 30 years. It
's wonderful to
learn, and it's a wonderful
friend for your whole life. So
keep this book close to you.
And I think there's a good
Chinese
translation. There's a good English
translation,
so keep it close to you. And I
started reading that book 14 years ago.  I'm
teaching, and I promised
to finish it, and if I survive,
if I survive a few more days,
I will finish it. I
want to keep my promise,
so we will finish this book this
week, and I'll give us a round of
applause.
The tradition of this line is that if you, if
you are in the audience, you have to
teach next. Really, this is no
joke. I know
you might not have been to every
class in 14 years. I don't know anyone else has done anything
except me,
but give me
this if I need to cry. I'm asking you,
we will
finish this week, and I ask you to
pass it on and teach it to other people.
My job is over for this one,
and it will be passed on to you,
even if you haven't been there the whole time.
That's
okay. You can listen to the audios,
or watch the videos, or you can
read it. It's not that
difficult, but it's better with
a class. But I have taught this whole thing,
and if you are teaching Lamrim, then do
your best. Nobody is perfect,
nobody is perfect. Maybe you just
have to try. Please
try it and pass it on to your
students, to your friends. I
have passed it on to the  My
girlfriend's mother passed it on to my wife, and
we'll finish the book this week
if all
goes well. The whole book is about
800 pages long, roughly 6000 English
pages, and we're very close to finishing it.
When I started
years ago, the very last part of the book
is about how we should meditate, and I thought it was
a good strategy to
teach the end of the book first. That's what I thought 14
years ago about shamatha and vipasana,
about deep meditation. So I
taught it first
because you should
meditate on every stage of the teacher's teaching,
and every time your teacher
teaches you a stage, you should
meditate on it. That's why it felt
logical to me to
teach the meditation beforehand, which
comes at the end of the book. Then you can go through the book
and
meditate after each section. So, it's a TR
tradition to
proceed this way. We have three main
sections, which are different
motivations
of people for learning the book.
Some
[music],
you say, they do
n't want to be a dog in the next life. They do
n't want to go into the...
The lowest motivation, the
lowest motivation to be here in this
room, is to
not fall down
when I die.
It's very unusual in
this
world to get into the course.
You have to
think about what happens after your
life. So before you get into the course,
you have to
think about dying. And I
went to Prinon, to university, not
something where you had to think about what you want to be in
your next life. As a
basic requirement, but anyway,
this book
starts with the day of your death, and
then it goes deeper and deeper. The
minimum motivation
is that you don't want to fall down.
You
want to at least be a human.
And everyone thinks they'll be a human in the
next
life. So in my part of the world, in
the Western world, we don't believe
that we'll live again when we
die. The people who
believe that say, "I
hope I have at least that much life experience," and
not so much as... or
all these people think that way. But
coming back as a
human is very, very
unusual, very
rare. And if eight people do come back as a human,
it's very, very
unusual. So the reason for
this book is
also to come back as a human.  Can
you at least
come to programs? Maybe you can find your own
kimono.
Okay, that's the mini, the
minimum motivation, the lowest. And
the second motivation is, I don't want to go back
to a place where I have to
die. I don't want to go back to a place
where I have to lose my family, my mother, again.
I don't want to go back to such a
place.
I want to go to a place
where we don't have these problems. And
the third motivation is, I want to
become a Buddha because a Buddha can really
help
countless people at the same time. There are
no limits, and it's
fun. I don't know if being
called a Buddha is such a serious thing.
I think it is. It's a lot of fun
to do. It's fun to
help others. Today I
went to a coffee shop. I cleaned the stalls for
the
staff, and I enjoyed it very much.
And imagine, you
can do that for billions of people
at the same time. You can
babysit for the whole
planet. That's my
plan. We, my wife, we sit
somewhere in the sky, and we babysit
my
niece
sometimes.
Bye. And then you know it
's
difficult to babysit for two-year-olds. She's very sweet.  We
bought such a big school bus,
and in America,
school buses are
yellow. We bought a school bus,
and you can take off the roof,
and there are lots of little children
inside. The child can sit the little
children in it, and a child drives, and
then she can put all the children in,
and then put
Sel in the bus. It's so cute,
and her name is Sis,
and she rides along, she rides along,
and she tries to get in the bus.
That means she thinks she's
so big, right, not even
her foot will fit in, but she
tried to get her foot in.
So, to look after a two-year-old is a
difficult task for
Grandpa when all the women go out and he
says, "Grandpa, open the child, open the child!" Then help!
But then imagine you can
be a babysitter for
billions of people. I think that's cool. I
think I'll do it. I'm looking forward to it.
I've worked really hard to become
a babysitter for 8
million people.
And then you go to the Buddha headquarters,
and then they give you a
planet. What's my planet? This one?
Okay, well, I'll put it on it. No
problem. And then
look at this whole planet. I think
that's cool. That's the
ultimate motivation!
I want to babysit the planet, to
look after this whole planet
until I, if someone on
my planet dies, then I'm not a
good
babysitter, so almost the whole planet, but
she thinks I still have to, I still have to
expand, I have to look after the whole
planet,
so we're in this part at the
end of the book
[Music]
we learn how to babysit planets
and there are
six
famous perfections that a buhatwa ma,
a batwa, wants to become a planet and
you make a
decision, you don't just think about
your family and your
country, you want to babysit the whole world, it seems
difficult but it isn't,
but I think two-year-olds are
harder, the whole
plan, and what I want to say is
fun, it's good to help someone not
to
die, I like to have fun every day, that's what
I like to do, and I can
tell you, being a bat,
that
thing is serious, you're too serious, oh
death, we have to save a planet from death
like a hero, it's just
fun, it's like a big party, that's
the best party you've ever been to,
looking after 8 million people, you don't feel
stressed, another planet, one  is
not enough, so we started learning to do this
and we
continue. There are
activities one has to learn,
and we will go through these six.
We went through giving,
so the first is
givingana, the perfection of giving.
We have completed that, and now
we are at
Shila
Paramita, morality or
ethics. And now we begin,
okay? And
by the way, I am very proud that
people are still coming back after yesterday. Go on,
yesterday was a very difficult
class, and I am very proud that you came back,
and I am very
happy that you came back.
Yesterday was the
test. If the people who give up yesterday do
n't come back, we will make the
first class very
difficult, and the people who
work very seriously, who don't listen, will
also be affected. And then we will do the
second class, and that's what we are doing
today. I'm
pointing at this on the screen, so
you don't have to learn it. You don't even have to think about it.
I'm planning for your next
life, and you think you want to, but you won't learn it.
But you
will. I agree with you, maybe
you won't learn it in this life, but
I'm not planting anything for the next life. Don't
bring Sam into your cool. You ca
n't learn this in a
week, so do it.  Don't overthink it, don't take it too
seriously. It's a very
unusual language, so I would have
always studied it. Has anyone studied this
language? There's an old
tradition that this language fell from the
sky, and I do
n't believe that. Linguistically, this language isn't
connected to any other. It's a very
unusual
language, and very good. Buddhism is very
important to
teach,
and I'm speaking from experience. You don't have to worry. Don't get upset. It
's not like
your school days are coming back to you.
I'd love to be
easy next time, baby. If
I plant the right
seeds now, but don't take it too
seriously. How do we practice the
perfection of ethical living?
Perfection is a difficult
word. Sanskrit is
paramount, the Himalayan
language,
but it's
a strange word because it's a
perfection, but it's also not. In
this case, perfection means that
morality
is perfect. You never stole $5 from
your mother. If you had
this
idea as a child that you are perfect, it doesn't mean that. It means that
if you
try, then it will lead you to
Buddhism. That is a
perfection.  A
perfectionist to make it perfect.
It's not
perfect yet. Someone here I
know right now is perfect in morality. It's
perfection, and
param means the vastness of the ocean. If
you're in Los
Angeles and a big storm comes and sweeps into
the ocean and you land in
Japan, that's when you reach the other
shore across the
ocean. There's the English word "
exit," which is the place where you
go outside. So, the English comes from the
Sanskrit "parameter," meaning to go to the
other side. That's
perfection. When I teach the
steps along the
way, I like to
use pictures, and I call them "idea images" for
short.
I like to show a picture,
and then I want to
teach you what the picture means. And
then later, when you
're teaching next week,
the pictures help you
remember. Pictures are very
helpful; a picture is worth a thousand words, let's say
roughly in English. Here's a
picture. Yes, I call it
the decision to
get rid of the trash, to lead an ethical life.
You decide to get rid of your
trash,
and then
he quotes what
bisavara means, like the way of life of a
Buddha, how one becomes  Babysitter for
a Planet, this is a manual on how to
translate a babysitter for a planet. It
was written 1300 years ago and
I'm going to read it to you.
So, this very important
word means "the"
and "B" means decision to
give something up. B means decision to
give something up.
For example, you can give up meat. You
can make a decision: I do
n't want to be involved in the
killing of
animals. Then I don't want to participate.
I don't want to be one of those people.
So, I can give
up eating meat. My
teacher, he's
Tibetan. They eat a lot of meat. We
say we can't grow vegetables
and the mountains are so high,
so we eat
meat. So, anyway, when I
lived in the monastery, I gave up
meat.
That was a little
difficult. When my teacher introduced me to other
teachers, he said, "This
is Mike. He gave up meat, but he did
n't give up his negative thoughts." It was made
fun of.
Okay, and then something interesting. He
was older, maybe
57. That's not
old. He had to have an operation,
and he came back from the hospital,
and he
said, "I will, I will give up meat."
And I was... I
always had to... I had to  I didn't
eat it, but I had to cook it, and
then he told me I shouldn't
eat meat anymore. He said
I had to have an operation,
and now I know how it feels
and I don't want to
eat meat anymore. And in the end, he said
maybe I'll give up meat now too.
That means
bongma. Boma
means to give up hurting other people.
B means I'm
making a decision. I don't want to
hurt people anymore. I
'll do my best not to
hurt people.
And sometimes, when you're in terrible
pain, like when you're in the hospital
and the doctor has to cut you open,
then
maybe you'll also get more compassion for
animals. And sometimes
bongma also means sadness. You
feel the
pain, and when you're in pain, then
you also know I don't want to
cause pain. I want to
try to help them. I do
n't want to
kill them. Cutting them open
means giving up, the
decision. The decision
to hurt other people is the second
perfection
of morality and
ethics. I'm
tired, and a wonderful, beautiful
story. I'll come back later. I put a
screen down, but the one that was so very, very, very famous
years ago is the most
famous.  A summary of the moral code,
written by
one of our translators, was
translated 5 years ago.
Shing, yes,
finished the commentary. Yes,
applause! A
very, very difficult commentary. She finished it.
In his
famous poem, Joh Kaer said
the definition of ethics, of
morality, the definition of the
second perfection is here.
This
means if you decide
not to harm other living beings, then that
is morality. Then it is ethical. And
then,
very interestingly,
traditionally in the very old
school, abidama,
physical and
verbal morality is physical and verbal: I
will not kill, I will not
stand, I will not have sex with
another person your partner
has. And then verbal: I will not
lie, I will not
talk about others, I will not engage in gossip, I will not speak.
Three with your body and
four with language. What is
harder to control? I think
the mouth is much harder to
control. So, to give up this seven,
the old form of morality. But
something is missing. What is that?
Yes, what are you doing in your thoughts?
In the old form of Buddhist
morality, you focus on what you do,
what you say. And as a scholar,
he said, with the
foundation, along with
The
root cause of what is the root cause
of breaking and doing is what you
think, and you can't let that out of
the perfection of
morality. You can say
morality is what you say, but in
Buddhism, the most important thing is what
you
think. And you can break your morality,
and no one knows about it. Inside,
you can think completely parallel things.
Sometimes you're
surprised yourself; you didn't know you could
think such terrible things.
Maybe a thought comes along: I'd
like to run this person over,
and you think, where does that come from?
Your mind sometimes does truly
terrible things. You don't like it,
and you don't say so, but no one else knows.
That's also morality in
Buddhism. Shan Shepherd is very, very
famous. Additionally, there's an addition from Z.
Kapper:
hurting people with your body and
hurting people with your words,
and the thinking
behind it, is very
clear. Deciding to
give up these things is
morality.
Kom
komba. If there's a G or a B word,
then it means meditation.
Gomba. If you take out the B and the S, it means getting used to
something.
And the Tibetan word for
meditation comes from the old word "etwas sich sich an etwas" (something, something to
something).  to get
used to and the deeper meaning of
meditation is to
do something in a certain way. That's what it means in very
old
Sanskrit, to be. Anna means
to
do something, and that means to bring yourself into something new,
and that's the meaning of meditation,
and that means to transform yourself into something new.
It's a very beautiful
word, and that's similar to...
and here says the perfection, the
perfection of
morality. If you're really good at it, if you're
really good at being
careful not to
hurt others, being super careful
is morality. That's
ethics. Okay, he's given a definition.
After you've
given a definition, then come the
different
types. There are three different
types of ethics in
Buddhism. I have many old
friends here
with different projects. It's so
much fun to
finally be able to talk about Buddhism
just in this room. It's like
breaking out of prison. There are three types of...
Shila
morality
comes from the old word
Schill, which
means to refresh, to feel cool. When
I walked through the city today,
it's a Schilang. It's not so hot, it
's not too
cold. In English, we say
crisp, crisp apple, crisp apple.
Crispy or fresh,
and
then it calms your
thoughts, and that means
morality. So it has three types. The first is
Buddhist
morality: never hurt others. That's the
first level,
meaning bad
behavior. So look, even if you can't
be a bishop,
so if you can't even give someone your
arm, then at
least hurt them. That means the first
type of morality: hurt other
people. And then there's this one who
says, "
Now I have a financial problem.
I gave my money
away yesterday." He's like a
magician.
Okay, you find money, okay,
100. I need more investors.
[Music]
No, no, I'm not asking, I'm
not asking for money. I
have to follow
morality and not hurt other people.
Come on, three
tastes: the morality of not
hurting others comes in three different
tastes, and all three are quite
classic
types of
morality. So
basically, now for
100 llar, and shout the
answer out.
I don't pay for shouting out.
Then,
MdE, what are the
three traditional
moralities? I don't choose from the...  The one with
the microphone, the one who's addicted, wait, wait, it was
louder, must kiss the microphone, I
think they're the primers, the
[music]
was great,
100, the Buddhist gels come in
three flavors like chocolate, vanilla,
strawberry, the first ones
are hurt, nobody else, then come
the B gelytes, the B gelytes are
interesting, they're promises, 64
promises that you make,
your life, you give, your whole life,
so the first ones, that you do
n't hurt someone, and with gels,
you want to help others, and those that
plant the seeds in your mind to become
a planet babysitter,
and I think I
mentioned it yesterday, we're going to have a
Buhisadwa geltte ceremony here, some of
my friends asked to give gels,
I do
n't really do that, I'm making a contract there, there's
a place here an
hour
away, and that was one of the, one of the
greatest
masters, arrived in Japan, what's his name again,
yeah, so this guy, unfortunately I didn't
understand, six times he tried
to come to Japan, six times and five times
his boat sank, but on the
sixth time it happened and  Then
he
went to the emperor and he gave them vows,
and this temple is still
in Kyoto, it's so beautiful. I did
n't go with my friend,
I
thought that would be the time to give
the satwa vows there.
That's in March
when the
sakuru blossom blooms, then
the bodhisadwa vows also open. We don't know yet,
we don't have a date yet, we
also need approval from the
government and it's all still
uncertain, and maybe we'll even be at the
beach. Anyway, those are the
second type and the third are secret,
the secret
vows, those are bodhisadwa vows, they
are super
charged. Do you want to know how my
teacher
introduced these GTEs? And they are
secret, and they are
secret,
but I will teach it next year
somehow.
But he says I want a quote from
Atisa, and that is a famous book
that was written exactly 1000 years ago.
What does "the light on the path" mean?
Z
brotherhood, a very famous
definition of the first stage of
morality, so the
first vow you take is SOA in
Sanskrit.  It's
pratimokaa and it
means
individual
freedom, meaning one
after the
other. Why for 100? Why is it called one
after the other
freedom? Do we have so much money, darling? So
what is one after the other? So, is it
the freedom part? That
's maybe 50, but why
one after the
other? Everyone who individually
takes this principle gets
freedom. You get to 100. I don't give to
anyone. I'm not that wildly
generous. Yes, pratimokaa
means if you protect the principle, if
you maintain it, then you will achieve freedom.
If you don't
adhere to it, you won't
achieve freedom. And that's why it's called
individual
freedom principles. So, whoever
can adhere to it will be free, and whoever ca
n't adhere to it won't be free.
Okay, cool. So, there are
seven types of
pratimoka
freedom principles, not
them, and we have to explain that.
We have to talk about it. So, I've
made some notes for you, and here, about the AA,
AA doesn't take the daily principle.
It says a daily principle: hello, it's a
day. Why?  Should we count them?
Normally we say there are
eight
free vows, and we say that a daily vow
is the first one. And Al Ticha
says a day. What's that supposed to mean? So he does
n't include it in his poem. He
says they are, and here are
the people who take vows for their whole life.
In the modern world, we should
say the lifelong women's
vows. They are so old, from the
time in India when women did
n't have equality and
men had more rights. And
secondly, there are the men who take
lifelong vows. The
first
two of the
seven, and the third is...
excuse me, that's second. Now,
what does "
nun" mean? They
have
about 10 to 13, 15 vows, and then
four. And then there's a category number
5, and that means
advanced nun. It was more
difficult for a nun to become a fully ordained nun; they
had to practice much more seriously
and keep the vows longer.
First, they got
the beginner vows, then the
intermediate ones, and then the
advanced ones. 200,
53 vows for one
Monk 64
more why do they have
why do they have more votives they are more
intelligent and can remember more votives
we taught them
to teach it this way
[Music]
so where is the rest of his
heart and now he says something
interesting
AA
says if you
keep one of these seven vows also the ten
votives this person
is ready for the
bodhiste do you understand what just
happened in this room
all those who dream of
taking bodhiste war votives in a place where
a bodhiste war votive was given
1000 years ago
you ca
n't take votives if you can't
keep the base votives
I'm trying to read you the contract here
if you want to
take the 64 votives
they are
fun the super fun votives
but you have to agree to the base
votives too so just
understand
okay you don't get the votives without
the
base say
g
means it's a hard word do
you have the
karma to come back do you have enough good
karma your bodhiste vow to
come here or will your plane be
delayed so your your
B bank account will somehow
go into the red and doesn't mean SAS like
good SAS like
good luck you are lucky
to take hazy gelpte and I can't
say and that's something in your
own gas what that came in your mind
it's trillions of years old I have
no idea maybe you are before more will
I die do
n't you have enough good karma for that
h you good K to
come here we don't hope that
if if
you think oh yes I really really want to do that that
also helps to have
than just to
come here be his boat
sank five times he is a great master
what shouldn't I
say there so
you understand so if a
great master comes with the boat that
sinks five times to give
bodad maybe then your
plane will be too
late
so if you book a flight don't make too close now
make strange
plans came a week
before and try to visit every French
restaurant in Koto
in that
time
seriously
okay tell me if I
if I don't stop then tell me no you
want do you need the
BAS this bas of basic morality
why the seven but  Where they are
n't interesting if you also take the
secret teachings,
the Diamond Teachings, the
secret teachings, S, they,
B, if you are a monk or a nun
[music]
then you get extra credit, then it's a
little easier. It's not
necessary to become a monk
or a nun to get the
secret teachings.
Everyone here in the room can
get them if you have taken B,
but
if the foundation,
but the best and most
successful, is if you
are a monk or a nun, and now
you tell me why,
based on this theory, why is it that the
more morals you try to maintain,
the better you will be able to keep your
secret vows?
So we had
problems translating this,
complicated. Don't tie your spices
so tightly, if I
understood correctly. It took us a month to figure out what that was supposed to mean.
As always, a monk or a nun, they
are much more careful, they are
used to being careful even about small things,
so they can
probably be more successful in the Diamond Way. But
everyone here in the room can study the Diamond Way, but you can
also not study the Diamond Way
if you don't take the teachings, but,
but
Generally, since
people have a
history of
Nagas, like dragons, they are
clever
dragons, and
worldly gods who took them
could
practice them. You don't have to
be human to get them,
so what's
better?
Generally, any kind of morality that
prepares you for
the rites is better. You do
n't have to take the bishopric to
become a monk or nun, but
monks and nuns who have taken the bishopric
are
much more powerful. They have an
upgrade to business class or first
class, first class, Diamond Way.
Some people say, "
What is the
lowest
freedom?" You can say a day
is
freedom,
or the one from
Flying's rites. I will not
kill a human being. I would not
stand for anything of value. I will not have sex with
another person
who is in a relationship. I will
not lie about having seen the freedom
directly. These are the
basis
of number
five. Say again,
I agree: no alcohol or drugs,
chemical
drugs, and the
old book. Alcohol or
drugs, and you  You agree never to
use them again in your life. I
wasn't born a Buddha, and I was
born a Christian, and I was a
happy Christian, and I had good
experiences in the
church. But many of my
friends, when I started
studying with my teacher 30
years ago, he said first thing, "You ca
n't drink. You can never drink again in your life."
And I almost bowed down to him.
I was 20 years old, and I
said, "God,
I mean Buddha, bless you,
and why?" And I said, "Alcohol ruins
my family. Alcohol ruins my
mother, my father." I
watched for 20 years as alcohol
ruined my family and
ruined my family's happiness, and thank you. I love
Buddhism. That's a good start.
If now, if
the lowest morality
includes drinking any alcohol
again, then I'm in.
Then that's a good
system because I
saw as a child what alcohol can do to good
people, but alcohol can make
them worse and worse. Do
n't come to God and say, "But what
if I want to have a glass of wine with my
grandma?" There's
a trick: you take the
wine, and she wants to drink wine, then
you give her...
Wine, and then you pour some yourself,
and then you spill it. I
can teach you, I've done it.
With me, the floor is completely empty.
So there's a big exception in
Buddhism. If you
want to take, try to stop them. You do
n't have to, only in this way. I'm saying this to those who...
I prefer to present the list
positively.
I don't like to say
no killing, no standing still. I like to
say
protect life, protect others, protect the property of others, protect
marriage.
Just say nice things to
people. Don't waste your language
with blah blah. Then rather keep your mouth shut. Do
n't be
happy when something bad happens to others.
And you
know,
and basically, you don't have to understand. You don't have to take anything
if you
follow these... It might be the cheap way to become a
businessperson.
Okay, the
BAS... I agree, don't hurt other people.
What is the second level of
morality? The first level is,
at least, please don't hurt anyone, and the
second level exactly helps
people. We gave a lecture in
Peru at the Business
University. We
had breakfast with the president of
the university. You were there too, and he asked,
can I...  Ask a question,
and he asked me about the
different types of ethics in
Buddhism, so at
least don't
hurt anyone, number one, and secondly, help
others, and then we think
we'll get there,
so all the types of morality to
help others, and here's a
list, I have 10 minutes,
right? It can include a person,
one who has taken their bodily functions
and comes to the temple, like when I
first
came to my teacher's temple, that is,
I love that, we do
n't go to a temple, you
go to a
temple, you have to go in like this, he made me go,
that was the first
day, when you don't even know, you go to a
temple, you go in, that means we don't say
we visit a temple,
we say we meet the D and your
thumbs are in,
and that is, if you are born
like an animal with paws, that's how
you go to a temple, and good
to eat today, hello, just
doing that is the second type of
morality, keeping your hands properly in a
temple, another type of
morality, and showing
your respect to your teacher and also your
other
students, basis of
morality, second of morality,
sitting in class is the second
type of  Morality, what you do is good karma
just by sitting here. If you
fall asleep here, you do good
karma. I mean, pass
the class,
meditate and
think, so on the
plane on the way home,
think about what you heard. That's
a kind of morality, a kind of
Buddhist
morality. And then
later, he
says you have to go under
that, an agreement in a
Buddhist
teaching, a basic contract between the teacher
and the student for two years. If
you're in class,
just by being here, you've
agreed to teach later. You're
not allowed
to sit in class later, or to
teach.
Where for 100? Where did he give his first
Buddhist teaching?
Everything was, he says,
in a car, everything
wrong, 100
away. It was
Einito. If you're Mexican, then
you know what I'm talking about.
[Music]
Yeah, a Volkswagen. There are many
Volkswagens. I'm talking about a
small one, a
Beatle. One person fits in there quite
comfortably. My
first class was the one, the postman, the one who
asked me something. No, I'm not asking
for more money, he
said. In America, you do
n't really tip.  To the
postman, but if you don't do it,
sometimes the mail gets lost,
you know what I mean?
Rimrock Stanley,
okay, I already gave a tip last week,
and he asked
what you're doing here. It's
a Buddhist
temple, and he asked if I could
study it too. And my postman was
my first
student,
and my teacher, can I teach him in the
kitchen? And teacher, no. And
you go out into the
temple, he sits in the back of the car and in the front,
and then you teach him. That was
very, very... He's breathing down his neck.
So when I say you have to teach
Buddhism, you have to
teach Lamrim because you
learned Lamrim, then
I mean also in a coffee shop and also to
your family at
dinner. And you don't have to say, "These
are the three types of morality,"
and
so it doesn't have to be like that.
Encourage other nice people.
That
is, make a hotpot for your family
and America, have
Thanksgiving dinner and make something
good to eat, and then just ask, "Is it
okay to
kill others?" Very gently, very gently. Can
you let something slip in?
Teach Buddhism also as a friend
in the
car. It doesn't have to
mean...  Speaking to many people,
it has taken
me 50 years
to find you. You won't find people in
12 weeks. Start with one
person. Stuff not
gone. Yeah, are you buckled up? Let me tell you
something about morality. That's all.
Second,
morality.
Everything you try to
perfect
is morality.
All these activities
are
morality. I have a Chinese friend
who drove his Tesla too fast.
He didn't know
how fast he could drive. I'm
not going to start here, but have
I
done this yet?
[Music] One more sentence.
All the activities of a person. One of
the three types of morality.
[Music]
Simply when you
came to Lamrim class and learned about the stages of the
path, morality itself is learning the
steps on the path.
Following this class for 14
years, every day you've sat here,
you've
practiced morality. Morality is being a good
person.
I have 12 minutes left,
Tim. The third type of
morality: the first is not
hurting others, the second is wanting to help others,
and the third
is helping everyone in the world.
And for that, there is a special
practice,
and that you...
and those are the...  Four ways
to
treat your students, your pupils, are very
nice. If this
class, if the third one is
on, you have a
moral responsibility
to share it with other people. In Buddhism,
we say if they want it,
we shouldn't bother others with our
religion.
You're Jewish, do you want to talk about
Buddhism? I say
no, I don't really want to
hear about it. We're not
allowed to
bother people who don't want to
hear it.
If you're on the plane,
you want to hear that I've been learning,
and they say no, I'm texting
my mother right now. But if they say yes, I
want to, then we have a responsibility to
share. That's the big, big
difference. We have
different
religious people who come to the door and
knock, and my wife can never
say no. She's met good friends this
way, and she
gives them cake and coffee, and they
talk about religion.
But we're not
allowed to do that.
If the student
says "dala," then it means they want to
learn, and if they don't, then
nobody asked me. So if
you flew to Kyoto and you were
here for an hour, then I think you
want to learn, so then it's
okay for you.  To teach me even without
the mandala,
so we'll take a
break and when we
come back we'll talk about the
four ways to divide the D with others,
so a 30-minute
break because there will be a queue for
the toilet.